<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning excommunication, as executed by officials, and concerning the common law writts, de excommunicato capiendo and de cautione admittenda, for the punishment of persons excommunicated and their deliverance from the punishment vvherin is examined whether the execution of the former as executed by many, be not a profanation of a great ordinance of God, whether by the second the subjects is many cases be not unwarrantably oppressed : as also by the difficult granting of the other, which is a common law writt, and the right of every subject to be obtained without difficulty : discoursed in a letter to an honourable friend / by one who is a friend to English liberty.</title>
            <author>One who is a friend to English liberty.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6708</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13705389</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13705389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 842:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning excommunication, as executed by officials, and concerning the common law writts, de excommunicato capiendo and de cautione admittenda, for the punishment of persons excommunicated and their deliverance from the punishment vvherin is examined whether the execution of the former as executed by many, be not a profanation of a great ordinance of God, whether by the second the subjects is many cases be not unwarrantably oppressed : as also by the difficult granting of the other, which is a common law writt, and the right of every subject to be obtained without difficulty : discoursed in a letter to an honourable friend / by one who is a friend to English liberty.</title>
                  <author>One who is a friend to English liberty.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Wrote before the Parliament which sat from March, 1678, to the end of May, 1679, and now published."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Excommunication --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101481:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101481:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning EXCOMMUNICATION, As Executed by Officials. And concerning the Common Law Writts, <hi>De Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and <hi>De Cautione admittenda;</hi> For the puniſhment of perſons Excommunicated, and their Deliverance from the puniſhment.</p>
            <p>VVherein is Examined, <hi>Whether the Execution of the former</hi> as Executed by many, be not a <hi>profanation</hi> of a <hi>great Ordinance of God;</hi> Whether by the <hi>ſecond</hi> the <hi>Subjects in many Caſes</hi> be not <hi>unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably oppreſſed;</hi> As alſo by the <hi>difficult granting of the other,</hi> which is a <hi>Common Law Writt,</hi> and the right of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Subject to be obtained without difficulty?</p>
            <p>Diſcourſed in a Letter to an <hi>Honourable Friend,</hi> by one who is a Friend to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty.</p>
            <p>Wrote before the <hi>Parliament</hi> which Sat from <hi>March,</hi> 1678, to the end of <hi>May,</hi> 1679, and now publiſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Acts. 19. 15.</bibl>
               <p>Jeſus I know, and Paul I know, but who are you?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Job. 6. 25.</bibl>
               <p>How forcible are right words? But what doth your arguing reprove?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Hujus <hi>[Scilicet Papae]</hi> poteſtatem, huic cum divino munere ſublatam eſſe manifeſtum eſt, &amp; ne quid ſupereſſet, quo non plane fractam il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius vim eſſe conſtaret, leges omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, decreta, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inſtituta, quae ab Authore Epiſcopo <hi>Romano</hi> profecta ſunt, prorſus abroganda cenſuimus.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epiſt. Hen. 8. praeſixa libro cui Titulus, Reformatio Legum Eccleſ. impr.</hi> Londini. Anno 1641.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst</hi> at the Bible and Three Crowns at the lower end of <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> 1680.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101481:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101481:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his highly honoured Friend,</hi> J. B. <abbr>Esq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE charitable deſign of this Paper is (amongſt the many oppreſſed, which His Moſt <hi>Sacred Majeſty,</hi> in conjunction with His two Houſes of Parliament, hath made to go free,) to ſhew you one ſpecies of Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whom no Parliament hath had leiſure as yet to take notice of; who beſeech your Honours, that you would alſo allow them to be <hi>Priſoners of hope,</hi> being ſuch as no <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> will relieve. The Adverſaries of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> could not be ſatisfied that their Miniſters were outed of their livings, and (many of them) of their whole <hi>Subſiſtence</hi> for <hi>themſelves, Wives and Children,</hi> and by <hi>another Act</hi> forbidden to reſide in any place where they might expect a relief from the Charity of good People, but many of them have been purſued to <hi>Excommunication</hi> upon the <hi>Statutes</hi> for not <hi>coming to their Pariſh Church,</hi> (though certainly they being Miniſters of the Goſpel, were themſelves obliged to Preach on <hi>Lords Days,)</hi> and being <hi>excommunicated,</hi> they have had the old <hi>Common Law writ, de excommunicato capiendo</hi> taken out, and ſome of them upon it have been detained 3, 4, 7 Years; nor at the end of that Term, have their mercileſs Enemies been willing to let them out, or let them take the <hi>advantage</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> to come out, and amongſt the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary people, not a few have been thus uſed, to the ruine of many Families, the exhauſting great Sums of Money moſt injuriouſly from many perſons, and the prejudicing the Trade and Commerce of the Nation; and all this by the abuſe and prophanation of a great Ordinance of God, that I mean of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> uſing what was ordained of God for the <hi>purging of his Church</hi> from perſons not fit for its holy communion, meerly to ſerve their <hi>Luſts</hi> of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> and <hi>revenge;</hi> and to keep worthy Patriots from being choſen Members to repreſent their Countreys in your <hi>Honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> among many inſtances of which nature you had one the laſt <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Berwick</hi> in the caſe of Mr <hi>Ruſhworth:</hi> and you have one yet more notorious this Parliament in <hi>Leicesterſhire:</hi> as if their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101481:3"/>
               <hi>Excommunications</hi> diſſeiſed men of their <hi>Freehold,</hi> or (which indeed looks more likely) the Subjects ſubjection to their Courts brought them into the Notion of <hi>Bond-men.</hi> A practice which (if not timely by your Honours taken notice of, and reſtrained) will give the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noply</hi> of <hi>ſuffrages</hi> into the hands of <hi>Regiſters, Officials</hi> and <hi>Proctors.</hi> This, Sir, certainly will give our <hi>Honourable Senators</hi> juſt cauſe to inquire,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether Excommunication as now practiſed by Officials in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Courts, be not an horrid profanation of a great Ordinance of God, and fit to be reflected on by our Governours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether the impriſonment of perſons Excommunicated, by vertue of the writ</hi> de excommunicato capiendo, be <hi>not</hi> as practiſed a great <hi>oppreſſion of the Subject, and worthy of a Parliamentary conſideration and relief?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether the writt</hi> de cautione admittenda, <hi>being the only relief provided by Law for perſons ſo impriſoned, hath its juſt and free courſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Honour and Glory of God being the firſt and principal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, as well of great Councels, as of particular perſons; the firſt of theſe queſtions deſerveth and challengeth the preference, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions of this nature.</p>
            <p>Whatever be the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>ſome Forreign Divines,</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hath been ſaid by <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> or others to the contrary; It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, <hi>That our Church looketh upon Excommunication,</hi> as an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and inſtitution of Chriſt, for the keeping of the Church pure</hi> and <hi>unſpotted</hi> (as the Spouſe of Chriſt ſhould be) and this appeareth as from other evidence, ſo from the very form of <hi>Sentences</hi> at this day uſual in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> which they uſually begin <hi>In Dei nomine,</hi> in the Name of God, and they tell us, they proceed to ſuch ſentences, <hi>Chriſti nomine prius invocato,</hi> having firſt called upon the Name of Chriſt, <hi>ac ipſum ſolum Deum praeponentes,</hi> ſetting God alone before them. Our Articles, 1552 tell us,</p>
            <p>That excommunicate perſons are to be avoided, as being <hi>rightly cut off from the unity of the Church, and ought to be taken of the whole multitude of the faithful, as Heathens and Publicans:</hi> Which Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is alſo verbatim in thoſe 1562, and manifeſtly allude to that Text of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 17. generally judged to be the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of this <hi>Ordinance under the Goſpel;</hi> Nor can any thing be clearer, then the declared Judgment of Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Goodrick,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cox,</hi> Dr. <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> Dr. <hi>May,</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101481:3"/>
Mr. <hi>Lucas,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Goodrick;</hi> who were the 8 Perſons, (part of 32 afterward intended) who according to Three Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> made in the caſe, were appointed by the Letters Patents of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> Dat. <hi>Nov.</hi> 11. in the Fifth Year of His Reign, and authoriſed to reviſe the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> and out of it to draw up a body of <hi>Canon Law,</hi> which ſhould alone be uſed in <hi>England,</hi> who did meet and draw up ſuch a body, (though King <hi>Edward</hi> lived not to confirm what they had done by His <hi>Royal Sanction,)</hi> as may be ſeen by a Book, called <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſiaſticarum;</hi> printed 1670, and reprinted 1641. Theſe great Divines tell us in their Chapter about <hi>Excommunication;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is a Power and Authority derived from God to his Church,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. That the Church receiveth <hi>theſe keys from Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To multiply words in this cauſe were vain, for none that ever owned <hi>Excommunication,</hi> owned it in any other notion then as an <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt's. And there is no pretence for any to ſeclude men from the enjoyment of the means of Salvation, but Chriſt who is the Lord of the Church. Which being granted, the true notion of excommunication is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a power granted by Chriſt to his Church, to remove lewd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or ſuch as are Heretical, and are pertinacious in their lewd opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and practices from the Communion of the Church, in the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the fellowſhip of Chriſtians, till they reform:</hi> Which exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreeth with the notion of it given us in theſe words by Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and other of our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> in their Book called <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſiaſticarum.</hi> De Excommun. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Excommunicatio poteſtas eſt, &amp; authoritas ad Eccleſiam a Deo profecta, quae facinoroſas perſonas, vel de religione noſtra corrupte ſentientes &amp; ad ſuam improbitatem adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcentes, a perceptione Sacramentorum &amp; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reform Leg. Eccleſ. Ed.</hi> 1641. p. 159.</note> etiam Chhriſtianorum fratrum uſu, tantiſper ſummovet, donec ſenſus ſanos recollegerint, &amp; ſalutarium cogitationum apta ſigna dederint &amp; poenas etiam ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticas ſubierint, quibus ferocia carnis comprimitur, ut ſpiritus ſalvus fiat.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Excommunication being thus univerſally agreed, to be a <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> it muſt as to the uſe of it, be regulated by the Divine Rule. <hi>None can Excommunicate, but thoſe who are by Chriſt thereunto appointed. None ought to be Excommunicated, but by warrant from the</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101481:4"/>
               <hi>word of God,</hi> and <hi>Excommunication</hi> muſt proceed with that <hi>gravity</hi> and <hi>leiſure,</hi> which <hi>the ſame word hath directed.</hi> And every one ſeeth that where any thing of this nature is done otherwiſe, It is an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>profanation</hi> of the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and a <hi>woful abuſe</hi> of a power which none but God could give unto any. That this power is given to the <hi>Church</hi> from Chriſt, is agreed on all hands: Whether it reſteth in <hi>the whole Church,</hi> or in the <hi>Governours of the Church,</hi> is the onely queſtion here.</p>
            <p>That this power according to the inſtitution of Chriſt belongs <hi>to the whole particular Church, to whom the offender relateth,</hi> is to me as clear as the light. According to the Primitive direction, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. If he would not <hi>hear the Church, he was to be us an heathen and a publican.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks to the whole Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4. <hi>That in the name of the Lord Jeſus, when they were gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and his ſpirit, with the power of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, they ſhould deliver ſuch a one to Satan;</hi> and Excommunication being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſecluſion of the party from the <hi>enjoyment of Ordinances,</hi> but from the <hi>intimate Communion of the Members of the Church;</hi> It is very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd for <hi>Officers</hi> in a Church, to think of ſecluding any from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of thoſe who will yet have fellowſhip and communion with them; and conſonant to this was the Judgment of the Ancient Church, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at none ought to be excommunicated <hi>diſſentiente plebe,</hi> without the conſent of the people, from whoſe communion he was to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. And without doubt as to the <hi>Major Excommunication,</hi> it is the moſt rational thing imaginable, and our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Book called <hi>Reformatio legum Eccleſ.</hi> pag. 161. cap. 6. on this ſubject, ſaith; <hi>Totius Eccleſiae conſonſus quanquam optabilis eſſet.</hi> That the conſent of the whole Church is deſireable, but becauſe it can very hardly be procured, they ordain as there followeth. <hi>That no one perſon ſhould exerciſe this power,</hi> &amp;c. but that the <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop, or ſome other lawful Judge, with a Juſtice of the Peace, and the proper Miniſter of the place where the party accuſed dwelleth, or ſome other appointed by him, and two or three other Religious Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> ſhould meet, in <hi>whoſe preſence after a due and full handling and weighing the cauſe, the party ſhould be Excommunicated.</hi> Some will have <hi>Excommunic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion</hi> the <hi>Act of the whole Church</hi> onely denounced by the <hi>Miniſter.</hi> Others will have it the <hi>Act of the Presbytery</hi> or <hi>Governours of the Church:</hi> Others who fix the Government in <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> will have it the <hi>Act of the Biſhop;</hi> but our <hi>Primitive Reformers</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101481:4"/>
would not have him doe it, but with a <hi>Juſtice of the Peace,</hi> the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the place,</hi> and <hi>two or three other grave Miniſters, who all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhould hear, examine, and ponder the cauſe, and agree, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon deſerving ſuch a puniſhment, which they might then Decree, and the Miniſter of the place might Publiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being an inſtitution of <hi>Chriſts,</hi> it ought alſo to be denounced againſt none but ſuch onely, as he hath in his word appointed it for, which is not onely determinable from the <hi>letter of Scripture,</hi> but from reaſon concluding from the <hi>End of the Inſtitution.</hi> In the letter of Scripture, there is no pretence for <hi>Excommunication</hi> of any, but for ſuch crimes as <hi>ſhut a man</hi> (without Repentance) <hi>out of the kingdom of God;</hi> thoſe are either <hi>damnable Hereſies,</hi> according to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to <hi>Titus,</hi> Chap. 3. v. 10. <hi>An Heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject,</hi> and the example of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 20. who delivered up to Satan <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus, having made ſhipwrack of Faith;</hi> Or <hi>lewd</hi> and <hi>vile practices,</hi> for which we have a preſident in the <hi>inceſtuous perſon,</hi> mentioned 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and conform to this hath been the conſtant judgment of the Church, and our aforementioned <hi>Reformers</hi> in the book, and place aforementioned determine, that they muſt be <hi>perſonae facinoroſae &amp; de Religione noſtra corrupte ſentien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; ad ſuam improbitatem adhaereſcentes.</hi> Leud perſons, corrupt in their ſentiments of Religion, pertinaciouſly adhering to them, and yet more plainly in their third Chapter, which I ſhall Tranſlate:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Excommunication ought not</hi> (ſay they) <hi>to be uſed in minute offences, but upon atrocious horrible crimes, when the Church is grievouſly ſcandalized, either becauſe Religion is overthrown, or good manners perverted by them, of this ſort are thoſe of which St.</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith,</hi> that thoſe who do ſuch things, ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of God, or ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God, or becauſe of thoſe things the wrath of God cometh upon the children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience. <hi>Theſe horrible wickedneſſes ought to be puniſhed by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, ſo as they who are guilty of them ſhall be thus puniſhed, unleſs they in time reform, and when they are admoniſhed, withdraw themſelves from theſe courſes, and be willing to ſatisfie the Church for the dammage it hath ſuſtained from their offences: for Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not to be uſed, but when men have hardned themſelves in their wickedneſſes, which happeneth two wayes, either when being call'd to</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101481:5"/>
               <hi>anſwer for ſuch offences, they will not appear; or if they do appear, they will not obey the admonitions of Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the opinion of holy <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and <hi>Taylor,</hi> (two of our bleſſed Martyrs) and thoſe other good and learned men, that lived in King <hi>Edwards</hi> dayes, in the very beginning of the Reformation, and were known to be none that could be juſtly called <hi>Presbyterians</hi> by any who underſtand what <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are. Beſides, this is evident from the end of this <hi>Appointment,</hi> which is keeping the Church pure as the ſpouſe of Chriſt. Now how can the communion of any Church be corrupted, but either by <hi>damnable Hereſie,</hi> Superſtitious or <hi>Idolatrous worſhip,</hi> or by the lewd converſation of its members? from whence what was ſaid before follows, that none but damnable Hereticks, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous, and perſons lewd in their lives, and Pertinaciouſly reſolved to continue ſo, can by any right, or authority from Chriſt be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.</p>
            <p>3. Further, it being an <hi>Inſtitution of Chriſt,</hi> it muſt be uſed, as by thoſe perſons whom he hath appointed to it, and towards thoſe perſons onely whom he hath willed ſhould be ſo puniſhed, as a means in order to their Reformation; So with <hi>thoſe circumſtances and in that order onely which he hath preſcribed,</hi> what is that? let us look <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 16, 17. we ſhall find it muſt be after <hi>firſt, ſecond, and third ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 10. <hi>After the firſt and ſecond admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition;</hi> Conformable to this hath been the practice of the Primitive Church, and ſuch was the Judgment of our firſt Reformers, as may be ſeen in the book beforementioned, cap. 4. pag. 160. I will trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the whole Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No Judge ſhall Excommunicate any perſon, unleſs he hath admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him once, and again, and a third time if occaſion be, that if it might be he might ſeaſonably reform his life, and there ſhall be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time allotted to the offender for him to think and conclude with himſelf, whether he will obey the admonition. But he that is rightly called [that is for ſuch crimes as Excommunication ought to proceed againſt] if he appeareth not prejently, runs the danger of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the premiſes naturally followeth, That it is impoſſible that the holy name of God our Saviour ſhould be more profaned, in the pretended uſe of any inſtitution of his, Then for them to meddle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101481:5"/>
with it, <hi>whom he never appointed thereunto,</hi> and for it to be applyed <hi>to thoſe whom he never directed the application of it unto,</hi> and for it to <hi>be uſed in a method or manner contrary to what he hath directed.</hi> And for this Ordinance, it is an inſtitution which he hath appointed for purging his Church from ſtubborn Hereticks and lewd livers, which he hath ordained his Church, and the officers of it, ſhould diſcreetly, and with great gravity, leiſure, and ſeriouſneſs, uſe in order to that end. Firſt, calling before them perſons accuſed of ſuch guilt, then gravely admoniſhing them, a firſt, ſecond, third time giving them due leiſure to think upon their pious and grave counſel, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and if they do not, then they are to declare them Separated from the Church in the Communion of all Ordinances, but ſuch as Heathens may communicate in, and ſuch with whom the members of the Church muſt have no intimate and unneceſſary communion with them, though they may buy and ſell with them, as they may with Heathens, and they ought to admoniſh them occaſionally as they meet them, as thoſe who have formerly been Brethren, <hi>not counting them as Enemies.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Let us now, Sir, Examine, how this <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>dreadful</hi> Sentence is made uſe of by <hi>Officials,</hi> for what end, upon what perſons, and in what manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Excommunication among us is <hi>decreed</hi> by <hi>Officials,</hi> who are moſt of them Doctors of <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Cannon Law,</hi> ſome of them but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few ordained perſons, but ſeldom or never by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of the place to which the concerned perſon belongeth; We in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed plead the neceſſity of Biſhops for jurisdiction, of which this is the main, but in practice confeſs there is no ſuch need, for perſons are <hi>cited, admoniſhed, Excommunicated, laid up in Gaols,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop</hi> never knows of it. For perſons not in orders to <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi> is an abomination not allowed in the <hi>Popiſh Church,</hi> and for any in orders to excommunicate perſons to whom they ſtand neither in the Relation of <hi>Chief Paſtors</hi> (as <hi>Biſhops</hi> are accounted) nor curates, or <hi>ſubordinate paſtors,</hi> is what is warranted by no Authority from Gods word, nor any true primitive Authority, nor the judgment, or practice of any other Reformed Church, nor the judgment of our own firſt Reformers: So that plainly the inſtitution is perverted, profaned and abuſed, as to the Adminiſtrators of it. But let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire further.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All Excommunications proceed <hi>upon contempt,</hi> and ought not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101481:6"/>
otherwiſe to proceed. This contempt may be,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) <hi>When perſons duly cited for ſuch Crimes, as by the rule of Chriſt men ought to be cenſured for, do not appear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) <hi>When appearing, they yet refuſe to obey the Eccleſiaſtical Judges admonition of them, to amend ſuch courſes and practices as according to the word of God they are to avoid, or if they perſist in, to be caſt out of the Church.</hi> For, our Officials cauſe men ordinarily to be <hi>cited</hi> to their Courts, not only for erroneous Doctrines, or for their leud practices, ſuch as <hi>Drunkenneſs, Fornication, Adultery, Inceſt, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, profane Swearing,</hi> &amp;c. but for any Crimes or Offences which they take their Courts to have jurisdiction of, which (as they make them) are almoſt innumerable; if they appear not as the day, they are preſently Excommunicated, though it may be, they were cited for not paying a <hi>Church-Wardens rates;</hi> and it may be where they were unjuſtly taxed, or a <hi>Proctors Bill,</hi> which it may be is thrice what by Law it ſhould be, or for not coming to <hi>prove a Will,</hi> and an Hundred ſuch like trivial things.</p>
            <p>If they do appear, and the Judge admoniſheth them to appear next day, and they fail, or to anſwer a Libel, which is illegal, and they are not in Law bound to anſwer<hi>:</hi> Or an Hundred ſuch like light things, they are again, if they obey not, Decreed Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate; So the puniſhment which Chriſt hath appointed for the moſt vile and flagitious Crimes, is dayly made uſe of to puniſh the moſt minute and trivial Offences; expreſly contrary both to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to the Judgment of all <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> and our own <hi>Primitive Reformers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. According to the <hi>Rule of the Word of God,</hi> the Judgment of all <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> and our own <hi>Firſt Reformers,</hi> Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought not to be agreed, or decreed by any ſingle perſons, nor before a firſt, ſecond, and (if need be) a <hi>third admonition;</hi> and thoſe ſo given, that the preſumed guilty perſon, have due leiſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with himſelf what to do, and to digeſt his pious admonitions. But the way of our Officials is to <hi>admoniſh thrice</hi> in a Breath, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I admoniſh you</hi> the firſt time, <hi>I admoniſh you</hi> the ſecond time, <hi>I admoniſh</hi> you the third time; <hi>I decree you Excommunicate,</hi> all in the Tenth part of an hour.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, I offer it to your ſerious conſideration, and the Reflection of any perſon of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Senſe,</hi> whether this be not as high a profanation of an Holy Inſtitution of our Saviours, as can reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101481:6"/>
be imagined: Nor had it been ſo long endured in this <hi>Reformed Church,</hi> had not <hi>King Hen. 8th. firſt,</hi> then <hi>Edw. 6th.</hi> dyed before they had called together the 32 Perſons which each of them was by Authority of Parliament, deſigned to call together to reviſe the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and compile one body out of them, as may be ſeen by the Act 25, <hi>Hen. 8th.</hi> 19. and another Act in <hi>Hen. 5th.</hi> time, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in the 3. <hi>Edward 6th</hi> There being but Eight of them called, and thoſe by <hi>Edw. 6th</hi> in the Fifth year of his Reign, (as appears by his Commiſſion, dat. 11. day of <hi>Nov.</hi> that year, and preferred to the book before mentioned, called <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum.)</hi> But that Excellent Prince dyed, before that he had added his <hi>Royal Sanction</hi> to that new formed ſyſteme of <hi>Canons:</hi> So as though we have had conſiderable <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip;</hi> yet, we have had none in Diſcipline, but <note place="margin">25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. 19. 14. <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note> proceed according to all old <hi>Popiſh Canons</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods,</hi> where they are not <hi>contrariant</hi> or <hi>repugnant</hi> to the <hi>Kings prerogative,</hi> or the Laws of the Land, which the Stat. reſtrains. I beſeech you Sir, ſeriouſly conſider<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether this practice be not apparently <hi>a profanation of a Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> and taking the <hi>Holy Name of God in vain;</hi> who hath ſaid, <hi>He will not hold him guiltleſs, that takes his Name in vain.</hi> If it be, whether it be fit any longer to be indured in a Nation that profeſſeth to Chriſt, eſpecially conſidering, that by the common Execution of this ſentence, in ſtead of purging out the rotten and putrid mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, the ſoundeſt members are cut off; I mean, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ſobereſt Principles as to Faith, and the ſevereſt Lives; and mens Luſts are ſerved inſtead of Chriſt Our <hi>Excommunications</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grown ordinary revenges of particular <hi>ſpight and malice,</hi> when they have a mind to get a perſon out of a City, or County, they know not why, or to be even with thoſe, that would not be awed to give their <hi>Suffrages</hi> for ſuch Members to ſerve in <hi>Parliament</hi> as the <hi>Officials, Regiſters</hi> and <hi>Proctors</hi> would have had. To all which is conſiderable, the eminent oppreſſion and ruine of many Perſons and Families conſequent to this practice, which brings me to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond queſtion propounded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether the Impriſonment of perſons upon the Writt</hi> de Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicato capiendo, <hi>be not (as practiſed) a great oppreſſion of the Subject, and a grievance worthy of a Parlimentary conſideration, for Relief?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Common Law</hi> is, That when a perſon hath ſtood Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101481:7"/>
40 dayes, the <hi>Biſhop</hi> may ſend into the Chancery a Writing, <hi>ſignifying</hi> ſo much, (which Writing is uſually made, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Hand and Seal ſet to it of courſe without his knowledge;) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the party ſuing for it, ſhall have a Writt, which is called the Writt <hi>de excommunicato capiendo,</hi> directed to the Sheriff, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to <hi>ſeize and impriſon the perſon</hi> concerned, where he muſt lie <hi>without Bail</hi> or <hi>Mainprize.</hi> This may be done as to any perſon who hath ſtood Excommunicated ſo long, but is ſeldom done, but where any <hi>Official,</hi> or <hi>Promoter,</hi> or <hi>Church-Wardens</hi> have a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular revenge</hi> to execute, or where the <hi>Regiſters</hi> want Money; But theſe Writts within theſe few years, have flown abroad at a very ſtrange rate. If the Regiſter can take any perſons, they will ſerue out 5, 8, 10 pound, and ſet them at Liberty. Others ſhall lie in Priſon during their pleaſure, till their Families be impoveriſhed and ruined for want of their Labour and care; and themſelves have contracted ſome fatal diſeaſe, that either they dye there, or ſoon after they come out, or live a valetudinarious Life ever after. My ſelf have known, One, a reverend Miniſter, kept thus 7 years, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother 4 years, others a long time<hi>:</hi> One poor man I knew, dragged out of his death-bed, (ſo it was then like to prove, and in few days did prove,) by Bayliffs, and his Friends enforced to redeem him for five pounds paid to the <hi>Regiſter,</hi> which proved but the dear purchaſe of a few hours life, abundance of ſuch inſtances might be produced. Theſe puniſhments are all inflicted by the civil Magiſtrate, he iſſueth the Writ to the <hi>Sheriff,</hi> whoſe Bailiffs by his precept ſeiſe the perſon, and whoſe Jaylour keeps them. Sir, <hi>I have oftenſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed to think how any intelligent civil Magiſtrate could anſwer this dealing with people before God.</hi> Admitting a perſon unduly <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated,</hi> (and it is not one of ten but is ſo) either for a cauſe which the Law of God will not juſtifie, (and that alone can juſtifie the lawfulneſs of an <hi>Excommunication,)</hi> or for cauſes, or in manner and methods which the Law of men will not juſtifie, onely the ignorance of <hi>honeſt ſimple ſouls,</hi> or their want of money keeps them priſoners. I would gladly know of him that can anſwer me, upon whom the blood and ruine, of theſe perſons or their wives and children muſt lye, and who ſhall account to God for it another day? For an account muſt be made, and the cry of the innocent ſhall be heard and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged.</p>
            <p>In the caſe admitted, here is plainly an Act of high <hi>unrighteouſneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101481:7"/>
               <hi>oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> and what before God amounts to no leſs then <hi>Murther</hi> or <hi>Robbery.</hi> The queſtion is, who is guilty of it? It is true, the Kings Name for form ſake is uſed in thoſe Writts, but he is not concerned in the guilt, nor knoweth any thing of it. It ſhall not lye upon me, ſaith the <hi>Curſitor,</hi> I did iſſue out the Writt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but that is the duty of my place to iſſue out any <hi>Common-Law Writt;</hi> Not upon me ſaith the <hi>Sheriff,</hi> I did but Execute the <hi>Writt,</hi> Nor upon me ſaith the <hi>Bayliff,</hi> I did but Execute the <hi>Sheriffs precept</hi> upon the Writt; Nor upon me ſaith the <hi>Gaoler,</hi> I did but keep him according to the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> Warrant. I do not think any one can be excuſed, who knowingly hath had an hand in the action. Neither the <hi>Official</hi> who decreed the Excommunication. Nor the Miniſter that publiſhed it, nor the <hi>Officials</hi> or <hi>Regiſter</hi> that ſignifyed in the cauſe; nor the <hi>Curſitor</hi> that iſſued out the Writt, nor the <hi>Sheriff</hi> that Executed it; nor the <hi>Bayliff</hi> or <hi>Gaoler.</hi> I am ſure in other cauſes at our Law, the Juſtices or other Officers illegal warrant will not juſtify the <hi>Conſtable</hi> or <hi>Gaoler</hi> for falſe <hi>impriſonmen.</hi> We had another Writt much of the ſame batch taken away by the laſt <hi>Parliament;</hi> upon which the <hi>Sheriff burned honeſt men,</hi> judged Hereticks by the Church-men. I would gladly underſtand who were guilty of thoſe <hi>worſt of murthers.</hi> The <hi>Sheriff</hi> there did but Execute the Common Law Writt in the cauſe, would that excuſe him, think we? It ſeemeth my Lord <hi>Cook</hi> did not ſo judge, for before he would take the <hi>Sheriffs Oath,</hi> he got the clauſe abated, by which he ſhould have been obliged to perſecute the <hi>Lollards;</hi> but admit, Sir, that all theſe inferiour Miniſters of <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> were excuſed, becauſe they do but Execute an <hi>unrighteous Law:</hi> The guilt muſt then lie upon thoſe that <hi>made</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>that ſuffer it ſtill to continue in force, having power in their hands to annul it.</hi> I take it to be true in Divinity, that no <hi>command of man</hi> can juſtify any <hi>Miniſter before God, in any act of impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety</hi> or <hi>unrighteouſneſs,</hi> much leſs <hi>alter the nature of the action,</hi> and make that <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>righteous,</hi> which is <hi>predetermined</hi> by the Law of God <hi>impious</hi> or <hi>unrighteous</hi> to aſſert any ſuch Atheological poſition, is in plain terms to make the Creature paramount to God, and a Controu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of his Creator; but if it would, ſtill the guilt muſt lie ſomewhere.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But, Sir, Doth it no deſerve ſome further deliberation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> hath <hi>any obligation from God upon him thus to corroborate Church-cenſures?</hi> I do know that our Common Law Writt <hi>de excommunicato capiendo</hi> ſaith,<hi>—qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a querelis Eccleſiae</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101481:8"/>
               <hi>deeſſe non debemus:</hi> But I want one Text of Scripture to prove any ſuch thing. The great ends of excommunication are</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Purging the communion of the Church.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Reformation of the offender.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt end is obtained by <hi>Excommunication;</hi> if indeed an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated perſon will intrude into the Communion of the Church, it is a breach <hi>of the peace,</hi> and falleth under the Magiſtrates cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance.</p>
            <p>For the Second end, A Gaol in ordinary caſes proveth a very <hi>inadequate medium</hi> to the Reformation of any perſon, and where it doth one good, it is found upon experience to do hurt to an hundred: Humane Nature is rarely tamed by ſuch rough applications<hi>:</hi> I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet knew any cured of their <hi>Nonconformity</hi> by being laid up in Priſon<hi>:</hi> 'Tis ſuch an Anti-Evangelical way of Cure, as hath not met with any ſucceſs, that can farther commend it. When our Bleſſed Saviour inſtituted the purgation of his Church, He ſpake not a word of a Gaol; He ordained, that his <hi>Church</hi> ſhould ſend for an Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Scandalous perſon, endeavour to convince the Gainſayer of his error, inſtructing him with all meekneſs, rebuking him with all gravity, by the Mouths of their grave Paſtors and Teachers. That if doing this once would not produce the deſired effect, they ſhould do it a ſecond, then a third time, waiting to ſee if God at any time would give him a heart to repent. If this would not do, That the Church being <hi>in the Name of Chriſt gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſhould declare ſuch a perſon cut off from the Communion of his People. This now done by perſons not guilty of the like or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Crimes, and clothed with the Authority of Chriſt, is a probable means to reduce the offender; however, the Church is cleared from ſuch a perſon, and its Communion is kept pure; though the Perſon be thus cut off from Communion, yet the Church ſhall not count him as an Enemy, but mourn over him, pray for him, admoniſh him as a Brother. How came in the Writt <hi>de Excommunicato ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendo;</hi> as if the Ordinance of God had not ſufficient Authority for its ends? For 300 years after Chriſt, the Church could have no ſuch aſſiſtance, nor do we read that it complained for the want of it, poſſibly here and there God might make ſome pertinacious <hi>Heretick</hi> or <hi>debauchee,</hi> an extraordinary Example of his Vengeance. He hath done ſo in our Age, in the caſe of Mrs. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> in <hi>New England;</hi> but that God ever did. This ordinarily for the firſt 300 years can be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101481:8"/>
proved by no Scripture, no Authentick Authority; But as the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Government crept up by degrees, ſo pretended Church Officers began to enlarge their jurisdiction, and to excommunicate for ſlight and trivial cauſes without any pretence of Authority from God, but meerly to ſubjugate people to their Wills, and get fees for <hi>Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Officials, Regiſters,</hi> &amp;c. They had no reaſon to truſt God any longer to vindicate their uſurped Authority, and to juſtifie their groundleſs and impious <hi>Excommunications</hi> and <hi>Anathemaes.</hi> They muſt therefore now call in the Civil Magiſtrate to do that which they could not expect that God ſhould ever do. Now come Writts to be invented. To <hi>impriſon perſons excommunicated.</hi> To <hi>take Apoſtates.</hi> To <hi>burn Hereticks,</hi> &amp;c. The Ordinance of God, was firſt turn'd into <hi>Ridicule,</hi> by dealing it out as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26. 18. <hi>the mad man caſteth firebrands, arrows and death,</hi> and moſt lewd and vitious perſons imployed to diſpenſe this grave ſentence, principally to be uſed againſt lewd perſons, ſo as every one that heard them, cryed out, <hi>Phyſician heal thy ſelf,</hi> and all ſober perſons thought they heard God ſpeaking to them; <hi>What haſt thou to do to declare my Statutes, and that thou ſhouldſt take</hi> my name, or my authority, or my cenſures <hi>into thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my words behind thee?</hi> and then the civil Magiſtrate was called in to help the Church, in her male-adminiſtrations, whoſe work indeed was to have <hi>whipt theſe buyers and ſellers out of the Lords Temple,</hi> and then the <hi>glory of the Lord would again have appeared betwixt the Cherubims, Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> would have appeared dreadful enough without the appendix of a Gaol. There was never any need of Gaoles to puniſh excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated perſons, till perſons came to be excommunicated for not paying <hi>Sextons wages, Proctors fees, Eaſter two-pences, Tythe-piggs, and Geeſe,</hi> not <hi>coming to the Pariſh-Church,</hi> not <hi>ſigning with the Croſs,</hi> not <hi>wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Surplices,</hi> not <hi>kneeling at the Sacrament</hi> (crimes not mentioned in the word of God) yea for <hi>preaching the Goſpel, meeting together to pray to God,</hi> or to <hi>hear a good Sermon.</hi> And it is not a Gaol will convince thoſe offenders that they do evil. <hi>Obj.</hi> But I hear ſome ſay, Theſe <hi>are all acts of diſobedience to Authority,</hi> and <hi>diſobedience is as the ſin of witchcraft. Reſp.</hi> Diſobedience to the Law of God, (of which <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpeakes) is indeed as the ſin of witchcraft, but yet every diſobedience to the Law of God is not to be puniſhed by <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication.</hi> It will be hard to juſtifie it to be the will of God, that perſons ſhould be excommunicated for every <hi>idle word, of which</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101481:9"/>
               <hi>they muſt give account,</hi> or for an 100 things forbidden by the Law of God, much leſs for all things forbidden by the Law of God. Nor is a Gaol the puniſhment ſet for every diſobedience to the Law of man.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But, Sir, admit a perſon were duly <hi>Excommunicated according to the Law of God</hi> (which not one of a hundred is, not one of ten duly according to the laws of men, witneſs the <hi>Judges</hi> relieving many by Writs of <hi>prohibition, habeas corpus, ſuperſedeas, &amp;c.</hi> and many more would be ſo relieved, were they acquainted with the law, or had they purſes to take the advantage of it;) yet I very much doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> with a <hi>ſafe Conſcience</hi> can ſend <hi>him to priſon,</hi> and ſo be a means of his ruine. My reaſon is becauſe <hi>he hath had no knowledg of his crime,</hi> further than that an <hi>Official hath told him, he hath been excommunicated</hi> 40 <hi>dayes.</hi> I take for granted, and I appeal to your reaſons, <hi>whether any Magiſtrate ought not to do what he doth out of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and upon certain knowledge?</hi> Our law ſuffereth not the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to grant an execution againſt any for forty ſhillings, till he hath been arreſted, and he hath heard what he or his Council can ſay in his own defence; but in theſe caſes, the Magiſtrate commands a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be impriſoned and ruined, and neither doth, nor may hear any thing of his cauſe. It is true at our <hi>Aſſizes</hi> and <hi>Seſſions</hi> Malefactors are condemned, to be <hi>whipt, branded, impriſoned, hanged;</hi> but the <hi>Sheriff</hi> who is to be the <hi>Executioner of theſe ſentences,</hi> hath his place there, and a liberty to hear the perſons caſe tryed, and he doth hear the caſe argued, ſo as that he is or may be convinced the perſon deſerveth ſuch a puniſhment, which done, as a Miniſter of God and of Juſtice he may proceed with a conſcience not rebuking him. But in theſe caſes, the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> hath no ſuch liberty, but proceeding upon the credit of the <hi>Official,</hi> and his ſuppoſed juſtice and honeſty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I cannot diſcern a figleaf to cover the nakedneſs of this, but what is uſually objected; <hi>That this is according to Law.</hi> The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which is no more then this; That this hath been a <hi>cuſtom in England,</hi> and <hi>there is a Common law writ in this caſe, formed by Judges in Popiſh-times,</hi> and not ſince corrected by <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi> If this plea be good, we have reaſon to bleſs God, that we were not burnt at ſtakes before the writ <hi>de combu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endis Haereticis</hi> was by the laſt Parliament annulled, there was then as much law for that, as for this. But is it to be wondered, that while the Nation was enſlaved to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101481:9"/>
the Pope, ſuch things ſhould be? A Magiſtrate under Popery, is but the <hi>Popes ſlave</hi> and <hi>Executioner.</hi> If a Magiſtrate would not do what the Church (as they call'd it) commanded, he was <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> his <hi>Nation interdicted,</hi> no Prieſts durſt perform any divine Offices in that unholy ground, and no ſooner is a Prince <hi>Excommunicated by them,</hi> but every ſubject is by them made a Traitor, authoriſed to poyſon, ſtabb, ſhoot him, or to riſe up in Rebellion againſt him, and all his neighbour Princes are armed with what authority the Pope can give them to invade him, and deſpoil him of his Dominions. Now that magiſtrates under theſe circumſtances ſhould have temptations, to burn, and hang, and impriſon men, never knowing why, or whether they were any way guilty of any thing worthy of any ſuch death or bonds, is no way to be admired. But that in a Proteſtant Countrey, where Magiſtrates are under no ſuch temptations to fear, ſuch things ſhould be done, is matter of juſt admiration; and no Magiſtrate ought to puniſh perſons under pretence of an uſage and cuſtome ſo to do, before they be ſatisfied, that they have deſerved ſuch a puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But further, Sir, Admit That the practice <hi>hath been Law,</hi> as they call it, that is a <hi>cuſtom in England time out of mind;</hi> and that <hi>it is law,</hi> that is, <hi>that there is ſuch a Writ ſtill may be had from Curſitors.</hi> This cuſtom had never been continued after the Reformation, had not <hi>King Hen.</hi> 8. and <hi>K. Edw.</hi> 6. both dyed, before they had perfected what by <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> they were to doe, and had began to doe, as appears by the Epiſtle of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and the Letters Pattents of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. prefixed to the book Entituled <hi>Reformatio legum Eccleſiaſticarum.</hi> It is true (as it may appear from the 13 chap. of that Book) perſons that ſtood Excomunicated 40 dayes, ſhould have been <hi>impriſoned.</hi> But therefore none was to be Excommunicated, but a <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> as well as the Biſhop, &amp;c. was to hear his cauſe, and if any Judge Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comunicated any, unleſs for ſuch notorious crimes as are mentioned chap. 3. and with ſuch <hi>deliberation</hi> as is mentioned chap. 4. <hi>himſelf</hi> (as appears chap. 8.) was not for a <hi>months ſpace</hi> to enter into Church, (unleſs to receive the Commuinion.) The Superiour was to relieve the perſon ſo injured, &amp; to annul the Excommunication, and the Judge that ſo Excommunicated, was to pay all the charges, and further pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at the pleaſure of the Superiour Judge.<hi>—That</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Judges may be afraid of bringing perſons into ſo great calamity without a moſt weighty cauſe.</hi> And may not ſuch a cuſtom be reſcinded by a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101481:10"/>
Statute law? have not many old Popiſh Cuſtomes been ſo aboliſhed? Is there not reaſon ſufficient? are not the cryes of people in all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Nation againſt it? Is there not in the skirts of it great quantities of the blood of Innocents? Have there not within theſe late years been more preſidents then ever before of moſt unrighteous Excommunications? were there ever before 100 in one place, 5 or 600 in another decreed <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> whoſe greateſt crime (whatever is pretended) was their giving free Suffrages for Members to ſerve in Parliament?</p>
            <p>Let Sir, I beſeech you the cry of the <hi>oppreſſed</hi> come before you, for your God doth not deſpiſe it. Let the <hi>honour of Magiſtracy</hi> be valued by you, let them no longer be mere <hi>blind Executioners</hi> of the <hi>luſts and malice of men,</hi> and vindicators of the illegal and impious actions of others. There is no Sober man in theſe Nations, but dreadeth <hi>Excommunication</hi> duly adminiſtred and applyed, becauſe of the authority of God in it. But they muſt then ſee it uſed onely againſt the enemies of God; <hi>Drunkards, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean perſons, Curſers, Swearers, Hereticks, Idolaters, Perjured perſons, Blaſpemers,</hi> &amp;c. and applyed to them by grave and holy <hi>Biſhops and Miniſters,</hi> before it, once and again, labouring to convince them of their ſin from the word of God, and adviſing them to reform, and waiting for their Reformation, and at laſt with <hi>grief and tenderneſs,</hi> with gravity and <hi>ſeriouſneſs,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to ſo dreadful a ſentence. How forcible are ſuch right words? but what or whom have our arguings of that nature reproved? who will, who can believe, that is <hi>bound in heaven,</hi> which by theſe hands, and for theſe cauſes, and in this ſlighty and praecipitant manner is <hi>bound on Earth?</hi> But, Sir, there is yet one thing more in this caſe, which I muſt crave leave to offer to your <hi>Deliberation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 Qu. <hi>Whether the Writ de Cautione admittenda, being almoſt the onely Writ for the relief of perſons impriſoned, upon the Writ de Excommunicato capiendo, hath its free courſe yea or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenderneſs of our forefathers for the liberty of the Subjects perſon, is obvious to every one, who hath the leaſt knowledge of the Law of <hi>England.</hi> If a man be unduly impriſoned, he may relieve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 1. <hi>By Action</hi> upon <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which provideth that none ſhall be impriſoned, but upon the judgment of <hi>his Peers,</hi> or <hi>by the</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101481:10"/>
               <hi>Law of the Land.</hi> 2. By the Writ <hi>de Odio &amp; Atia.</hi> 3. By the Writ <hi>de Homine Replegiando.</hi> 4. By a Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſedeas, Prohibition. &amp;c.</hi> in diverſe cauſes. But becauſe by an old cuſtom, perſons impriſoned at the Churchs deſire were not <hi>Bailable,</hi> There was a particular Writ deviſed for their relief. For our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers never intended the Subjects ſhould lye at the <hi>Officials</hi> mercy. The old Law therefore provided, that perſons ſo impriſoned ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Biſhop, and tendring him a <hi>Caution</hi> for their future obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to that command of the Eccleſiaſtical Court which they had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed, they ſhould be diſcharged, three legal <hi>Cautions</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. 1. <hi>By Pledge.</hi> 2. <hi>By Bond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 3. <hi>By Oath.</hi> The Subject tendring any of theſe might be diſcharged, by the old Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> under the greateſt Popiſh Tyrrany and Uſurpation. The Law further provided a Writ (if the Biſhop refuſed the Caution) to command him to take it. I will tranſcribe it as I find it in the <hi>Regiſter of Writs,</hi> immediatly following the Writ <hi>de Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> (as they ſay the God of Nature hath in ſome Countreys planted <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes</hi> in view of poyſonous plants. v. Reg. Bren. Orig. <hi>&amp; Judicialium, Londini,</hi> 1634.) <hi>It</hi> hath this <hi>Rubrick:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Si Epiſcopus idoneam cautionem de parendo mandatis Eccleſiae ab hujuſmodi excommunicato impriſonato admittere recuſaverit, volens ipſum per priſonam gravare. Tunc mittat amicum ad Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam &amp; fiat ei Breve ſic.</q>
            <p>That is, <hi>If the Biſhop having a mind to oppreſs the party, ſhall refuſe to accept a fit Caution, then let him ſend any friend to the Court,</hi> and let a Writ be made to him thus. Whence I obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That even in thoſe times, <hi>Officials</hi> were for keeping Perſons in Priſon contrary to all Law and Juſtice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That to remedy that Evil, this Common Law Writt was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is of the ſame Authority and as much <hi>Law,</hi> as the Writt <hi>de Excommunicato capiendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That it is not a <hi>Writt of Diſcretion,</hi> which may be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anted, or refuſed, as Officers pleaſe, and therefore to be obtained by <hi>Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> or <hi>Motions,</hi> but a Writt of <hi>Common Juſtice,</hi> which ought not to be denied by <hi>Curſitors</hi> to any Friend of the Impriſoned Perſon, coming to the <hi>Curſitor,</hi> and demanding it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. One thing I might further add, that it is upon the point, <hi>the only remedy provided in Law for perſons thus impriſoned.</hi> The party
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101481:11"/>
is not remediable by action, or indictment upon <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though he be not impriſoned by the <hi>Verdict</hi> of his <hi>Peers,</hi> yet he is impriſoned <hi>per Legem terrae,</hi> by the Cuſtom of <hi>England;</hi> nor by the Writt <hi>de Homine replegiando,</hi> becauſe that runs.<hi>—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be impriſoned for ſomething, for which according to the cuſtom of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>he is not repleviable,</hi> which is the caſe here; nor by the Witt <hi>de Odio &amp; Atia,</hi> for it is hard to make out that ſuch a Perſon is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned out of <hi>malice,</hi> though he indeed be ſo: Nor by any VVritt of <hi>Superſedeas.</hi> Indeed by the VVritt of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> a perſon thus impriſoned, may bring himſelf before the Judges at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> but they ſhall only judge whether he be <hi>juſtly Excommunicated</hi> from the <hi>Significavit</hi> which is before them. If the <hi>ſignificavit</hi> ſaith it is for <hi>contempt of the Court,</hi> being <hi>legally cited</hi> to anſwer for <hi>ſuch Crimes as are Cognoſcible in that Court,</hi> whether he were ever legally cited, or no, The Judges cannot relieve him, the parties Remedy lies againſt the <hi>Official,</hi> by <hi>Action of the caſe,</hi> and if he tryeth that way, if the <hi>Apparitor</hi> hath ſworn in the Court, that he did duly cite him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did or no; No action will lye but againſt the <hi>Apparitor,</hi> which is a lamentable remedy. If indeed it be contained in the <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificavit</hi> that he hath been accuſed for Crimes, which have been le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally proved, and he admoniſhed, and not obeyed, but ſuffered himſelf to be Excommunicated, and ſtood ſo forty dayes. And the party can make it appear, That the pretended Crimes were no Crimes, or not cognoſcible in that Court, or that they were not legally proved by two VVitneſſes, or that they have been pardoned, or that he offered the Biſhop caution, and he hath refuſed, or that he did not ſtand Excommunicated 40 dayes, or that the VVritt of <hi>Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> was not legally taken out as is limited by the Stat. 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 23. Or that he hath appealed according to Law; in theſe caſes he may be relieved by <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> or it may be a leſs chargeable way by <hi>Superſedeas</hi> (of which yet I am not certain if the VVritt be Executed) but the true legal relief of the Subject, if the Biſhop refuſeth Caution, I take to be by this VVrit <hi>de cautione admittenda:</hi> Though it be adviſable for every Excommunicated perſon, as ſoon as his Excommunication is publiſhed, to ſend one or two to the Biſhop, and to offer a <hi>Cautionary bond,</hi> which by Law he ought to take; if he refuſeth, it may be adviſable for him, as ſoon as he heareth the VVritt is out againſt him, to move for a <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> upon that ſuggeſtion, or a Prohibition (if it will bear it;) if not, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101481:11"/>
more adoe, to yield himſelf a Priſoner, and then bring this VVritt <hi>de Cautione admittenda,</hi> you ſhall find the VVritt in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of Writt,</hi> Printed in <hi>Lat.</hi> 1634. p. 66. in <hi>Engliſh thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The King to the Venerable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On the behalf of A. whom upon your denunciation, we have commanded by our High Sheriff to be Impriſoned, as a perſon excommunicate, and contemning the Keys of the Church, until he ſhall give Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to Holy Church, as well for his contempt, as for the injury done unto it. It hath been ſhewed us, that although A. aforeſaid hath often offered you a fitting Caution for his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the Legal Commands of the Church, that ſo he might have the benefit of abſolution; yet, you to our admiration have hitherto refuſed to accept ſuch Caution. And becauſe we will not have the ſaid A. detained in Priſon againſt Juſtice; VVe Command you to accept the aforeſaid Caution, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver A. from the Priſon in which he is detained upon the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Account. Otherwiſe we will do what is our part to perform.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Our wiſe Anceſtors foreſaw ſome Biſhops might refuſe Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Kings VVritt, and in that caſe they provided that the Priſoner ſhould have a ſecond VVritt directed to the High Sheriff of the County: The tenor of which in <hi>Engliſh</hi> is thus, as it ſtands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record in the Regiſter of VVritts in the place aforementioned.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The King to the High Sheriff of the County of <hi>L.</hi> Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. On the part of <hi>A.</hi> whom we Commanded you to Impriſon according to the cuſtom of <hi>England,</hi> as being Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and contemning the Authority of the Church, until he ſhould ſatisfie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And it was ſhewed us, that although the aforeſaid <hi>A.</hi> often offered the Biſhop a fitting Caution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet, the ſaid Biſhop (which we wonder at) refuſed to accept the ſaid Caution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Becauſe we will not that the ſaid <hi>A.</hi> ſhould longer be kept in Priſon, contrary to Juſtice, we Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you to go in perſon to the Biſhop aforeſaid, and in our <hi>Name</hi> admoniſh him, and effectually declare <hi>[Our Will]</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that taking the Caution of the aforeſaid <hi>A.</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the aforeſaid <hi>A.</hi> to be delivered from the priſon afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. And if the ſaid <hi>Biſhop</hi> refuſe in your preſence to do it, do you Command <hi>A.</hi> to be delivered from the Priſon afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, if he be kept there on no other account.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101481:12"/>
Our forefathers ordained that both theſe Writts might be had with <hi>ſicut alias, &amp; pluries,</hi> and not reſting here ordered an <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment</hi> againſt the Sheriff, in caſe he refuſed to yield obedience to the VVritt, which <hi>Attachment</hi> is in the <hi>Regiſter</hi> thus:</p>
            <p>
               <q>The King to His Coroners in the County of <hi>K.</hi> Greeting, If <hi>W.</hi> of <hi>W.</hi> Clerk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Cauſeth you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then put, <hi>&amp;c. W.</hi> the High Sheriff of our County aforeſaid to give ſecurity, that he ſhall be before us ſuch a day, to ſhew Cauſe why, whereas we lately commanded the body of the aforeſaid <hi>William</hi> to be Impriſoned according to the cuſtom of <hi>England;</hi> upon the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Ely</hi> his denunciation of him as Excommunicate, and contemning the Authority of the Church, until he ſhould ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Holy Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and we hearing that although the aforeſaid <hi>W.</hi> often offered the Biſhop fitting Caution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet he hath refuſed to accept it; by reaſon of which we often commanded him our High Sheriff aforeſaid, in perſon to go to the ſaid Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that he ſhould command the ſaid <hi>A.</hi> to be delivered, or ſignifie the cauſe to us, why he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed our commands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or to appear before us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and there to have our VVritt directed unto him; yet, the High She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff aforeſaid deſpiſing our Command to do the premiſes, or at leaſt give us a reaſon why he would not, or could not Execute the ſame, or appear before us the day aforeſaid; and regarded not to make return of our VVritt as we hear, to the manifeſt contempt both of us, and our Commands aforeſaid, and the no ſmall dammage and oppreſſion of the ſaid <hi>W.</hi> And we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, that you taking a fitting caution of the ſaid <hi>W.</hi> for his obeying the Commands of the Church according to Law, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him from the Priſon aforeſaid, if he be there detained upon that and no other account.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This, Sir, is the known Law of <hi>England,</hi> in the caſe of perſons ſo impriſoned; nor is it poſſible, any <hi>Engliſh Liberty</hi> ſhould be more fortified.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, My Lord <hi>Chancellor Hide</hi> (to whom we are beholden for more of this nature then this) by what Authority I cannot tell, turned this VVritt of <hi>Common Juſtice</hi> to be granted readily, and of courſe into a <hi>Writt of Diſcretion,</hi> making an Order, <hi>That it ſhould not be granted, but upon a Petition firſt offered for as to him, or the Succeſſive Lord</hi> Chancellors, or <hi>Lord Keepers;</hi> which Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition he took a liberty to grant, or not to grant as he pleaſed: (VVe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101481:12"/>
were beholden to him that he did not put the like reſtraint upon all other VVritts of Common Juſtice, for he might have done it by the like Authority.) Hence this Writt is not gained but with <hi>great charge and difficulty.</hi> I mean the firſt VVritt to the Biſhop: With what Juſtice this is done, Sir, I leave to you to determine.</p>
            <p>When it is granted, ſome Biſhops have taken themſelves to be at liberty, whether to Obey it or no. Some have utterly refuſed it, with the expreſſion of great anger, and threatning Perſons that they ſhould ſeek to come out of Priſon <hi>that way, [that is, by an eſtabliſhed Common Law Writt.]</hi> Yet, all that theſe men have to ſay againſt the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> is their <hi>not obeying the Law,</hi> and what Law can be plainer then this, or more ſtrong and juſt?</p>
            <p>When the Biſhop hath thus refuſed, (which hath been often,) I beſeech you, Sir, inquire what ſucceſs they have had, who have moved for the <hi>Second Writt</hi> to the <hi>High Sheriff.</hi> It hath been often moved for; I beſeech you Sir inquire what the reaſon is, that all His <hi>Majeſties Subjects</hi> cannot obtain theſe <hi>Writts of Common Juſtice</hi> from <hi>Curſitors.</hi> Why the VVritt <hi>de Excom. capiendo</hi> flies about ſo freely, and the VVritt <hi>de Cautione admittendâ</hi> is got ſo difficultly, when the latter is as good Law, and as much the demanders right, as the former; and the latter is <hi>for the Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subjects perſon,</hi> (which all the Law of <hi>England</hi> highly favours) and the former is for the reſtraint of it. If Sir, (till a <hi>Statute</hi> can be obtained to procure good mens Liberty from an old Popiſh VVritt,) the Law muſt have its courſe on that hand: I pray let it have its courſe on the other hand alſo; and let us not have the Liberty of our perſons at the mercy of every Regiſter that wants Money.</p>
            <p>Sir, I would not be miſtaken, <hi>I</hi> very well know, that in ſuch Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours Court, in the Court of the <hi>Arches and Delegates,</hi> &amp;c. many great and weighty cauſes of great and momentous natures are heard, and they at preſent have no engine, no method of Law, but by way of <hi>Excomunication,</hi> preſcribed to force the appearance of perſons to anſwer charges, or to force an obedience to their decrees. <hi>I</hi> have nothing to doe to direct my Soveraign, or a Parliament by what Courts or Judges, ſuch or ſuch cauſes ſhall be tryed, be they by whom his Majeſty and his Parliament pleaſe; nor is it reaſonable that they ſhould be without a Coercive power, both for appearance at their commands, and obedience to their Decrees; Your <hi>Honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> knows how to reach them out a ſword fit for their uſe, though
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101481:13"/>
they take not this which God hath laid up as <hi>Sacred</hi> in his <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> In our <hi>Common-Law,</hi> there is <hi>Judgment by default;</hi> in our little <hi>Courts,</hi> there are <hi>Amerciaments;</hi> In the High <hi>Court of Chauncery,</hi> there is an Attachment, and then <hi>a Writ of Rebellion.</hi> May it pleaſe you, Sir, to put any of theſe ſwords into their hands. But oh forbear this <hi>edged toole,</hi> which wounds both ſoul and body, and is not to be uſed but by them, to whom, and againſt them, whom, and in the manner where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our <hi>Common Lord</hi> hath ſaid <hi>ſmite,</hi> and <hi>what you bind on Earth ſhall be bound in Heaven.</hi> I beg your pardon for ſo long a letter, I ſhould truly judge it tedious, were it not upon an unuſual ſubject, and where the matter led me to it, and did I not know your great zeal for the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God,</hi> the Subjects juſt <hi>Liberty,</hi> and your compaſſion for many perſons, and families, already undone, and every day undoing, if your <hi>Honourable Aſſembly</hi> cometh not ſeaſonably in to their reſcue. Humbly committing them, Sir, together with your <hi>Honourable Aſſembly</hi> to the God of all Order, and Government, and the fountain of all wiſdom, I take my leave, and reſt, Sir, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101481:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
